[Anita] Hi everyone! Welcome to MagNetZ!
Today's seminar format is similar to previeous.
So we're gonna have about 25 minutes presentation
where we suggest you keep your microphone muted
and then we're gonna have some time for a
discussion, about 10 to 15 minutes, where you
can use the chat to to put your questions there or
unmute yourself and ask the questions. And at the end
of the seminar there is time for catch-up
informal and not recorded, and so you are welcome to
stay if you if this suits your schedule for today.
So I'm really happy to welcome today Priyeshu
Srivastava from University of Sao Paulo, Brazil.
Priyeshu will present today his work
on "Continental marine records for paleoclimatic
changes during the late Maastrichtian to early Danian,
understanding the role of the Deccan flood
volcanism". So Priyeshu please share your screen,
thank you thank you,
the floor is yours!
[Priyeshu] okay. Hi! thanks Anita and all the
attendees of the this seminar and
I would like to extend my thanks to Anita and Greig
for inviting to present in this seminar. This is my
first presentation on this seminar and hopefully
you will like it. First I would like to
explain about myself. So, I am Priyeshu, and I did
my phd from India and currently I'm doing a post
doc in University of Sao Paulo and visiting
INGV Rome. And I would like to [thank] my collaborators
and past advisors who helped me a lot during
this work, some colleagues from India and Brazil
and I would also like to acknowledge the grants
from India and Brazil without which the work
is not possible and support of
laboratories from different institutions.
To start with this presentation I would
like to briefly give a background about
large igneous provinces and its
climatic changes or impact on climate
during its eruption. So this is a pictorial
diagram taken from Font and Bond 2021. We can see
during the continental flood basalt
there is a enormous amount of
different gases which relates to different
climatic changes. For example, if we talk about the
CO2, CO2 leads to global warming as we also see
in the past 100 [?]. If we look towards the
modern climate, during the industrial
revolution time, in last 150 years, huge
amount of atmospheric CO2 has been released, and
which has led to decline in the *ocean Ph* by 0.1
moles. So we can use these past records
of content of flood basalt to understand
how it is going to impact the continuous release
of in anthropogenic CO2 into the atmosphere.
CO2 is one of the gases which leads to the
global warming and long-term ocean acidification
and changes into the ocean circulation. Snd the
other gases are SO2 which also leads to the
global warming. And when it moves towards
the established stratosphere it also cause
short-term cooling in the environment
and the other halogens which is like HCL and
other gases which leads to volume
depletion and further local acidities.
So this is a word map which shows the different
LIPs both continental and oceanic flood basalts
in the last 500 million years.
And on the right we can see the
extension of marine genera
and five big mass extinctions, which has been
also linked to the volcanic eruptions..
content of flood basalt eruptions.
So now my particular focus has been on the
Deccan flood basalt. On the right,
we can see the extent of the Deccan flood basalt
in the peninsula India, that covers a region
around 500 000 kilometer square of area, and
the original extent is estimated to be 1.5
kilometer square. The recent dating
has constrained the eruptions within 1 million
years, mostly within the 29r magnetic crhon.
We can see the pictorial or layered
floods from the *mahabaleshwar one of the
sections in the western *ghat mahalisha site.
There have been distinguished different
gases. For example, the total release of the gas is
for example.. SO2 it is estimated between 7000
to 17 000 giga ton, and for carbon dioxide it is 15
000 to 35 000 giga ton. And these extensive release
of the gases have led to a global warming in the
portion from two to four degree celsius, before
K/Pg [Cretaceous/Paleogene] from 66.3 to 66.15 Ma, and then followed by
a global cooling period for 150,000 years
leading up to the K/Pg boundary. The Deccan
flood basalt has been linked to the K/Pg boundary
mass extinction. And the other factor the other
primary cause for the K/Pg mass extinction has also
been meteorite impact in Chicxulub region, but
for now I am going to focus specifically on
the flood basalt and pre-K/Pg environment.
So, it is important to understand not
only the timing but also the volumetric
eruption model, and how much the gases are.. how much
the volume erupted during different episodes of
eruption. So there has been two Science
paper which appeared in 2019. One is based
on the Argon/Argon dating of the basalts in
the western part of region, and one is based on
the *gisthen, which is found in the red boles,
which I am going to introduce afterwards. So the
bole or weathering horizon is trapped between two
lava flows so both the chronology agrees in the
timing of the eruption. However a placement
of K/Pg boundary in the deccan is somewhat
different in both the papers, and following which
there have been several articles which tries to
focus whether the Deccan flood volcanism really
impacted the global climate at that time, or
its more and more eruption that happened
after the K/Pg boundary. So, these are two
places where they place the K/Pg
boundary in the Dececan flood basalt.
Follow paper shows that since
Argon Argon has a relatively higher
uncertainty or
error in the dating than uranium
lead, so these these models was that the pulse
eruption cannot be defined due to
the higher uncertainty in the Argon Argon ages,
whereas the uranium lead places the
four major eruption phases in the Deccan.
One big phase has been proposed before
the K/Pg boundary around 50 000 to
60 000 years before the K/Pg boundary
known as *pull out* formation, which we can see
from the biggest spikes, the biggest spike in this
diagram on the right. So, for continental
record, I studied the weathering profiles from
the Deccan traps value within profiles and I'm
also going to present some measures which
I obtained from the DSDP 356 core
from Sao Paulo Platform in the South Atlantic.
This is a paleogeographic map which shows
the locations of both sides with respect to
the volcanism, as well as the asteroid impact.
So for continental
record I used to study the
boles. So bole is very very uncommon term
in geology but it has been extensively
used in the Deccan traps. So, bole
means a brownish color earthy material
which has been appeared since
last two centuries, I think, the use of the term.
So, there has been mapping of
different lava flows from western *guard and
which we can see that more and more boles
appear in the upper part of the Deccan
chemo-stratigraphic or mostly in
the Ambenali formation, whereas these
boles are are really present in the lower
formations. So boles indicate a hiatus in the
eruption. Based on the higher occurrences
of these boles in the upper part that says that
more frequent eruptions has happened
in the younger formations.
This is a typical photograph of the boles,
where we can see start contact of the boles
with the lower floor basalt as the as well as the
upper flow basalt. In the inside we can see
an image which shows..higher
resolution image that shows
approximately four to five centimeter big
blocks of indurated clays, and as we
go towards the down it shows
smaller and friable blocks of red color clay.
Some other field characteristics I would
like to present..So, boles often are the
weathering profiles often considered as a paleo
soils. However the origin of different color or
different boles..different origins has been
proposed for these boles. For example, a
pyroclastic origin, where you have more and more
volcanic ahes and the paleosolis also. Some
of these origin has been also linked to the paleo
deposition also or shallow depression being
created from the erosion and the weathered basalts
being deposited and trapped by the upper flows.
So,
in the field, boles appear in different
colors, and sometimes we can also see transition
from one color to another. So we can see on the
left figure, this is a figure from *polar bear
near the *pune area in the western
part or peninsular region. We can see a
grayeish color brown bole which is greater than one
meter thickness at one end of the flow, and as we
trace this lava flow, which is more than 40 meters
to 50 meters, we can see transition of colors
from grayeish brown to reddish brown in a
vertical. At one
point we can also see transition from reddish to
reddish to grayeish brown in a vertical color change.
This is another example of the boles where we
can see a lot of calculating
the position. When we zoom the photograph
we can see that these boles have a particular
pencil shaped or our pencil jointing, and
a there was a model for such pencil joint there
was a model proposed by sarkar where they say that
when you when the upper law of root comes on these
weather profile they they create a dragging effect
which leads to the formation of pencil joints
however so my my focus has been on four different
colors of these bows from the polygon formation
and i did geochemistry and environmental magnetic
properties to to understand what climatic uh
what is the origin of these goals and what
climatic environment they represent so this
is a greenish colored bowl which is around 70
centimeter thickness and then brownish color or
soil is colored bull which is more than one
meter and even within the red color we can
see two distinct uh red uh based on the muscle
notation as well as the field of progressions
so I described them as a dark red bull
and light light is a color red wool
i did the mineralogy of clay mineralogy and fdi
spectroscopy to determine what type of mineral
content in this and so the greenish color bull
uh presents two minerals one is uh uh non-tonight
and cellulite so nautronite was could not be
identified from the clays uh separation so i
did the fdir spectroscopy and we can see more
iron and oh bond appearing in the fdir that
that confirms the president of monroe knight
whereas red pools is uh mostly montmorillonite
and hematite so obviously the hematite is
the red color of these red bulls whereas
the green is more salidonite and non-tonight
both both are greenish clay so probably these
uh indicates the coloring different coloring
of the both mineral control so the chemical
weathering of these walls was uh evaluated
and there is a ternary diagram which is acne
which shows the typical weathering trend of the
basalt in respect to the so the unaltered result
of the controls trap shows that cia chemical
index of alteration is below 50 and then when
weathering increases it goes towards 70 to 80.
and then we can see the greenish color goal has a
potassium enrichment so the potassium enrichment
in these welding profiles can either be from
metasomatic uh drain from the upper flows
or it can be from the volcanic as additions
here i did other chemical measurements moves
the trace elements and that also tells that
this potassium is from the volcanic ash sources to
evaluate the chemical uh i prefer the plagioclase
index of alteration as you can see there is
a potassium enrichment and that leads to a
a very very different chemical index of alteration
values which may not be valid if we are comparing
different types of both different types of color
boost so when we see the plagioclase index of
our trace and the values of all the bowls
fall between 76 to 81 which is not very very
different from each other and indicates a moderate
chemical weathering of these these goals and the
trace element mobility was also evaluated
uh to see how much the trace element has
enriched or depleted during the course of our
tradition so most of the bowls like red brown
and this shows that the gain of the gains
and losses of trace elements uh is lower
or minimum which is less than 40 percent in
various cases and that indicates either that
element release was it was not from the primary
sources or it was uh adopted on the clay surfaces
so the maze uh now i will come to
the environmental magnetic part
so we did the hysteresis iron mixing and fork
measurements of different colors of bulls
and tried to figure out in addition to the
chemistry what environmental magnetic can tells so
if we look at the sustainability data most of
the green or the green bows has very very low
values whereas the brown color goal has very
high accessibility values however it is more
it becomes more interesting when
we compare different types of
red color walls like the dark red and brown and
lightly colored and and we can see a decreasing
trend which which we cannot observe in
the chemistry data but when we when we
evaluate the magnetic accessibility value we see a
decline as we move towards the top of the profile
and when we evaluate the light color red
bull it shows an increasing trend so it
it's a two distinguished behavior of the red
color bowl so that may be either related with the
uh heating from the upper floors and that we
can also see in the component analysis more this
this component and hysteresis is for the
top samples top of the top sample of the
profile that indicates that more and more high
coercivity components are present in this whereas
some very magnetic as well as a high component
some high quality component of iron oxides are
also present in the light color blue
and when we evaluate the fork diagram
so we can see a distinguished uh work fault
diagram for all the different color of
samples and particularly the dark is
a dark red color bulls so is that very
very high coercivity which is going up to
around uh seven seven hundred milli tesla
uh 600 to 700 milli tesla the coercivity
component whereas if we evaluate
uh the light color the cohesivity is
uh around 60 to 70 or 80 80 milli tesla
we also did a work of pc for pca of different
balls and altered profiles i i forgot to write
the number so this pca is done on 26 samples
and we can divide three components or three
three n members em one e and two and a
m three so e m one which which is very
distinct than the other bowls and this e-m1
is for the greenish-colored bowl sample so
it appears so the green colored
bowl sample might indicate that
that the magnetite in these samples are the
magnetic minerals h probably from the volcanic ash
whereas em2 and em3 emp also has very low
cursivity component probably the residual
uh are altered tetino magnetite or magnetite
component and em3 which is observed in motion
of the samples or closer towards the samples
which is closest to what the end member three has
relatively higher cursivity
component probably from hematite
so the basic idea to do or
understand the alteration behavior of
these bowls was to find out uh whether
these sd classes such as scl or
the warming induced acidification has any effect
on the on the record on the on the trap on the
on the these value source profile so if because if
we notice the indian continent was moving at that
time from the tropical climatic zones and when we
have very high precipitation conditions uh then it
it's supposed to draw down the atmospheric gases
and probably leading to the acidic alteration
but these both from the chemical weathering trace
element mobility and as well as the magnetic data
we can see that they are altered but they do not
so they they do not show any acidic behavior if
we have very high hd behavior we would see
a loss of a higher amount of trace element
trace elements uh including the
radiation trace elements however
this can be explained from one of the
reasons that when volcanism happens
a mock radity condition was produced and the
smoke validity conditions might lead to the
transport of these glasses to the extraordinary
sphere and this then dispersal into the uh
into the globe or worldwide so this
may be one of the explanations for
for non-aesthetic signatures or near neutral
ph conditions for the alterations of these
these clays or profiles weathering profiles
uh towards the second part of my presentation
is to find out uh decon volcanism-induced
justification in the marine record so over
the past one decade with the advancement of the
chronology and more and more uh high resolution
measurements on the marine reports have shown the
globally mostly uh the tatian records from google
and without have shown a presence of low magnetic
sustainability zone before the kpg boundary which
has been interpreted that the loss of magnetic
signals is from the liquid flood volcanism induced
esterification so this this was this low emission
is shown in the whitish color chalky layer
previously it was interpreted to be uh
from the organic matter after the kpg
after the kpg eruption so the uh organic
matter got buried and that lead to the that
further populated down the section and removed the
magnetic signal however organic matter analysis
uh on this section shows that the
organic matter content was not very high
and a reappearance of bacterial magnetite
just before the kpg boundary further
has been proposed for destification uh from
the victim blood uh essentially gases from the
dictionary volcanism so these are the records
uh mostly from the font eric pond papers and
so to understand whether this estimation was seen
in the south atlantic as well i i studied dhtp 356
core in south atlantic and i did magnetic
measurements as well as the elemental chemistry
so we can see there is a decline in magnetic
accessibility just before the kpg boundary
here i would like to mention that the boundary
itself is missing in this uh section which is from
the highest uh i have marked with the bluish
color and the magnetostatic graphy as well
as biostereographic based uh these these are the
ages based on the biostatistic and magnetostatic
measurements so here we can see a low magnetic
accessibility zone which is also seen in other
uh nation report and so i compare this
result with the with the temperature data
which was the which was developed on the south
atlantic but towards the wall victory section
uh odp code 12 6 12 62 site here we can
see the latest market involving event and
during this event we can see the accessibility
was relatively high but when we go towards the
boundary there there we can see a decline in the
accessibility and it reaches minimum just before
the kpg boundary and then again rises the same
was seen this similar behavior was in an siren
more clear observations arm but arm is more uh
it's it's all almost very very low in in the
upper daniel as well as in the lower masturbating
section and very high fluctuating s receives
values that whereas the elemental geochemistry
for also stored uh a very high calcium value
in the low ms tune which is also seen in the other
records and the iron content is very less as well
as the titanium which can be a marker for the
teresinous impact was also during this introvert
to further go in more detail i did fault
measurements on selected samples of this
section so here it is more clear plot this is
the low ms zone uh which has been seen in the
deep nether theme and now in south atlantic
as well so we can see a declining or adjust
just below the kpg boundary all the signal or
magnetic signal in the parking it has disappeared
by then and we evaluated the they plot most of
the samples or i think all of the samples fall
closely to each other and in
the phd zone but when we see
there is a big diversion uh in the coercivity of
the samples just before the kpg and after the kpg
to further evaluate it to further evaluate these
variations i i calculated or plotted the y valued
plot of this section so so if you see the arm by
k and s ratio plot so we can see clearly these the
pre kpg and post kpg samples have very very low
uh low s ratio values and low arm compared to the
other uh daniel and master ktm samples and when
we evaluate s ratio and coercivity these samples
show that increasing coercivity of remnants and
the similar so one one thing is to observe is
that uh in the hrm and estrix hrm and cursivity
plot these samples does not show an increase in
hrm values which is an absolute measurement of
antipermanent content but rather only the increase
in cursivity so probably they indicate a indicate
of loss of magnetic signals from magnetite but
there is no clear indication in increase
in the concentration of anti ferromagnetic
so this may be an expression from the dilution
of magnetite and again there is one ratio leave
at all 2007 in 2007 proposed to l ratio and beca
that can be also distinct that can also be used
in distinguishing the different sources or the
changes in the coercivity so we can see these
again pkbc and post kpg samples at very high uh
coercivity but a very consistent l ratio values
i did isotopic measurements on the bicarbonate and
mercury anomalies on the samples mercury and
lead anomalies so uh and plotted along with the
contract uh volcanic eruption phases so first
i i'll try to explain the carbon and i c and
oxygen carbon and oxygen isotopic values so
it is interesting to note that the carbon
which is a signature in all the kpg sections which
declines at the kpg boundary from the master ethn
here what we see that the stepwise decline was
seen in the delta uh data 13c values which goes
which starts declining in the late master kit and
that warming even but we can see it it's not a
sharp change in the delta 13c but it's more like
a stepwise decline in related acceptance values
and when we evaluate uh the delta 180 so we can
see around point eight or two per mil changes in
the 18 values which is more fluctuating after
the kpg boundary mostly in the early daniel
warming event or which is known as dance c2 event
and the mercury anomalies uh i think i need to do
further measurements these are preliminary results
not the finalized so i i further need to measure
some samples in the lake mass medium but in the
daniel we can see there are two two huge spikes
which is uh if we look at the concentration which
goes more than 80 db around 80 people in these
samples which is uh coinciding with the ambient
light formation electrons in the liquid cloud
so to summarize uh the findings still now is that
when we evaluate the continental weathering or
bulls profile we can see these bold profiles
do not show uh aesthetic weathering or any
effect of sd dissolution on the magnetic
properties or or on the trees element mobility
but these balls rather so uh more constant
kind of chemical weathering intensity
but these can be divergent in when we evaluate
the heating effect from the upper basalts into
distinct red color bones but when we evaluate
the marine records which uh in this section so
is almost similar to the titan record where we
find low magnetic zones where the signals of
magnetite or detrital magnetite has been lost
which is also in in and the mercury anomalies
and the isotopic measurements are also in
accordance with the with the other kpg sections
so this is still not very uh finalized
interpretations of the data but
this is what trillionary observations
are on these two sides thank you
thank you priest let's uh let's give
a big round of applause um thank you
um very interesting uh work also a little bit
different from purely magnetic studies which
is also really interesting um i would like
to welcome people to ask the question now
you're welcome to amuse yourself or write
in the chat if you have any questions
well i can i can ask one since people when
people are thinking of their questions so um
comparing to the to the kind of south atlantic
records um why is the reason there is a job in
this limitation what's your observation together
with the kind of um little stratigraphic and also
deposition processes that would
cause that gap into the segmentation
okay so i have not particularly compared the uh
sedimentation right of the tatian as well as in
the south atlantic but this section where we
see dhtp356 there is a very high sedimentation
before the jpg boundary and the sedimentation
declined after the kinetic and more and more
terrestrial which is expected uh less carbon
less productivity and more and more continental
material coming after the boundaries so yes there
is a change and there is also a circulation change
which has been proposed before the or after just
into the paleogene transition but uh what i feel
in this there is no major change in the sources
of the sediment so the probably the sources is
each constant in this section maybe i don't know
if it answered your question or not yes thanks
is there any question from the audience
well i like okay great greg
has asked one question for you
yeah thank you very much it's really interesting
talk um when you're looking through your
um seventh course you see this distinct change in
in the susceptibility and the magnetic properties
and have you actually looked at doing any kind of
um you know magnetic extracts to actually look at
the magnetic grains and see if there's any uh
physical change within the grains themselves
yeah that's interesting but i haven't done it so
if still the work is in progress the idea will be
at some point to extract and to also figure out
i have done some some component analysis but
but still i need to do this physical separation
and acm and pm studies to see if these there is
a change in the grain size but but whatever
the property we see based on the arm it's
it's it should be a very big
change in the magnetic field size
i expect that i actually don't know
whether it will be but expectations are
thank you
um any any other questions
also the suggestions so all the suggestions
are welcome because this is not a finalized
study so anything i can
try to improve this further
yes suggestions are welcome also
the um i had i had one curiosity when you
were presented a different kind of goals
um and you were you were showing that there
is some gradient into the the single pole so
do you think maybe i missed this information if i
missed i'm sorry um do you think he is a matter of
of temperatures or is it a matter of just the the
chemism out that distribute across the bowl level
are you muted free i'm sorry sorry so i
agree so what was the first observations
between different colors was the uh obviously
the mineralogy the hemitatic color right so
so it's a tropical environment but it showed a
little bit of more currently the first was that
how the heating from apollo flu can change
the color of these these bones so in some
so what i try to figure out using different
bivariate correlations so the light color the
one i was presenting so the light color bowl
shows a progression like it's increasing so
as we expect because higher weather
part in the top and as we go down it's
uh it's relatively but when we evaluate the
chemistry it's all it's all the same but when
we look at the magnetic it's very different so
there is an increase towards the top along in
the sp and sd concentrations based on the kfd and
arm and other data which i did not present in this
so only the top part in light color it
shows that a heating effect is there
and when we evaluate the darkest red color where
we can see a very very high heating effect in all
the samples because as you go towards the top uh
it's only hematite present in the samples there
is no magnetite left and which we do not expect
in a moderate weathering profile right because
moderate weathering profile you expect a lot of
magnemite and other features so it indicates that
in this darkest matter it's all it's it's highly
heated but when you evaluate a profile where you
have this transition happening so if you expect
like a transition from in a horizontal perspective
where you have radius at the top and gray is
in the bottom there you can expect that heating
may have played a major role because it heated
up to like 20 centimeter or 40 centimeter and
the heating from upper law fluid did not
go towards the top towards the bottom but
sometimes it's very curious to see this horizontal
transition so if if i don't know how to how to
explain this horizontal changes from reddish to
grace in color so it may be either a little bit
of deposition setting where like the heating uh
continued up to some part but afterwards it it
didn't heat or it was more waterlogged situation
where the heating effect may not be there
but this is my experience i didn't i i tried to
show what type of bulls we expect in the field
and because it's not it's
not uniform in all the places
but i haven't worked on this horizontal
changes in the chemistry and and the magnitudes
okay thank you um thank you very much um if
there are no other questions i would like to give
creation another big round of applause and thanks
for for giving the this very interesting talk um
so uh to to wrap up i will
share again um this light
and um i would like to to to remind you that
now from this is the first talk of of eu eastern
atmosphere time slots they will go through from
june to august uh the next talk we have lined
up is on the 22nd of june with boris robert
from jeff said awesome 6th of july we have
yuichi ushui from karnataka university in
japan and we always welcome more speakers
to to fill up the the gaps and early career
scientists are very welcome everybody's really
welcome and um i hope you you enjoyed uh so far
the magnets you can find them recorded on the
youtube um in our youtube site and um thanks
again for for coming and see you next time
thank you so much for attending the
seminar thank you anita thank you